Today's דף *daf* is נ"א *nun-aleph*. We pick up at the bottom
of נ' עמוד ב' *nun amud bet*. Now the issue had been
we are on a little bit of a digression
and the issue had been whether a carcass of a kosher bird
נבילת עוף טהורה *nevilat of tehorah* which causes טומאה tumah, *tumah* when
you swallow it, whether it makes its when will it make itself
טמא tamei. *tamei* because actually there's a הלכה halacha *halacha* that something
that will itself become an אב הטומאה av hatumah *av hatumah* or
could be an אב הטומאה av hatumah *av hatumah* if it is
also a type of a food can make essentially itself טמא tamei
*tamei* as a ראשון rishon. *rishon* without the need of water, without
the need of touching anything else just because it has essentially the
potential of becoming an אב av. *av*. However, the requirement here is
that this dead bird be considered food because the טומאה tumah *tumah*
it's getting is the טומאה tumah *tumah* of foodstuff. Now we got
onto this discussion because there's a question about when does מחשבה machshava
*machshava* define something as food. If you need מחשבה machshava *machshava* it
has a questionable status and we said the argument was it does
not define it whether the thing is attached to the ground or
when it's alive animal because it can't become טמא tamei. *tamei* then
so the מחשבה machshava. *machshava* can't be meaningful. And the proof was
this case of the bird that you needed after it died to
decide that you were going to eat it or hopefully not eat
it because it's not kosher, give it to a non-Jew to eat
and then it would become טמא tamei. *tamei*. So that's the context
is when does מחשבה machshava. *machshava* matter in order to define something
as food, not when it's attached, not when it's alive. But the
specific discussion right now is is about the role of מחשבה machshava,
*machshava* for this bird and there was a debate of רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri* and the
Rabbis. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri *Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri* basically said you do not need מחשבה machshava *machshava*. If this
thing is going to be an אב הטומאה av hatumah, *av hatumah*
you don't even need מחשבה machshava. *machshava* and the Rabbis said you
did. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* although it really is a seems
to be a deep principled debate and that's what we're going to
focus on in a minute today's דף *daf* is that there's a
really fundamental debate about whether this thing needs מחשבה machshava. *machshava* at
all. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* for some reason and תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*
doesn't really even understand why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s bothering to do
this so I don't want to belabor the point, but the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* for some reason at the last few lines of yesterday's
דף *daf* said look, if it's a type of a if we're
talking about זילגי *zilgay* then in the זילגי *zilgay* everybody should agree
you need מחשבה machshava, *machshava* because they don't normally eat this type
of food carcasses of dead bird, carcasses of birds.
If it's in the cities well people there there's a much bigger
population and they have weirder tastes and they're less finicky and whatever
and anyway so in the cities people have a wider variety of
things they eat then everybody should agree you don't need מחשבה machshava.
*machshava*. So where are we talking? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
well we're talking in the city normally you wouldn't need מחשבה machshava.
*machshava* but since the case was that it fell into a vat
of wine that makes it a case where it's not so obvious
that people would want to eat it and that's where the question
of whether it needs מחשבה machshava. *machshava* or not. Okay so that's
fine but that's just pointing out that there are cases where it's
obviously food and you don't need מחשבה machshava *machshava* cases where it's
more not obviously food and you do need מחשבה machshava *machshava*. But
now we're going to continue because that really isn't the debate of
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri*
and the Rabbis. It has nothing to do with the wine and
whether this is a type of thing that's normally eaten or not.
It really is a principled debate about whether this whether dead birds
need מחשבה machshava. *machshava* at all. Since they're going to be a
source of טומאה tumah, *tumah* do they need מחשבה machshava. *machshava* at
all? And that's what we're going to see is intention, no intention
to consider it food. So although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* yesterday ended
off with what would seem to be a way of framing the
debate like we all in principle agree you need מחשבה machshava *machshava*
the question is do you need it in this case of a
dead bird in the city that fell into a vat of wine,
a much more sort of specific, you know, detailed debate, we're now
going to see and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* doesn't
understand why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* bothered with that because now we're
going to see that it really is a principled debate of this
thing that will be the source of טומאה tumah *tumah* do you
need מחשבה machshava, *machshava* for it to be considered food for it
to essentially receive טומאה tumah, *tumah* from itself? So let's take a
look.
Yes. Just a very quick question. So the reason why we differentiate
between נבילת עוף טהורה *nevilat of tehorah* and נבילת בהמה behema. טמאה
*nevilat beheimah tmeiah* is because a עוף *of* only gets טומאה tumah
*tumah* when you swallow it. Therefore it's a little bit
different than the cities and the villages? No. The cities that was
only a question about whether normally we assume people what type of
things we assume people eat or not and that whole difference of
cities and villages was
not less likely to eat a נבילת בהמה behema *nevilat beheimah*...
עוף *of*? Yeah, it's very strange because also why are they less
likely to eat if we're talking about non-Jews a dead pig or
a dead cow, I don't know. Let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. בן נורי *Amar Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri*. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is five lines from
the bottom a line starts with the word בן נורי *ben Nuri*.
Now going to just discuss the debate and it's going to be
this as I said a principled question of does this carcass of
a dead bird in order to be מטמא metamei, *metamei* itself need
מחשבה machshava. *machshava* or not? אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, בן נורי
קל וחומר kal vachomer, *Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, kal vachomer*. Here's
a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*. אם מטמא metameh טומאה חמורה
tumah chamurah שלא במחשבה *im metamei tumah chamurah shelo bemachshava*, if this
carcass of a dead bird can cause a strict טומאה tumah, *tumah*
without intention, meaning in your gut when you swallow it it is
a source of טומאה tumah *tumah* as an אב הטומאה av ha-tumah,
*av hatumah* and even if you're not planning on eating it, even
if you, you know, thought it was something else that you were
swallowing and you didn't treat it as food, לא lo, תטמא טומאה
קלה tumah kallah, שלא במחשבה *lo tetamei tumah kallah shelo bemachshava*, certainly
that it could also become the lighter טומאה tumah, *tumah* ראשון rishon,
*rishon* without planning on treating it as food and it should basically
make itself into a ראשון rishon *rishon*. And you don't need מחשבה
machshava *machshava* in this case, intention to treat it as food. אמרו
לו *Amru lo*, the Rabbis said back to him, לא
*lo*, no, אם אמרת בטומאה חמורה im amarta betumah chamurah, *im amarta
betumah
chamurah*... as opposed to here it goes down there. So גמרא Gemara
says, what does that mean? מאי אינה יורדת לכך, mai einah yoredet
lekach, what does it mean it don't go down there? Right, it
don't go down there? Right, it doesn't go down there? אמר רבא
הכי קאמר ליה, Amar Rava hachi ka'amar lei, this is what they're
saying back then. לא לא אם אמרת בטומאה חמורה שכן אינה עושה
כיוצא בה. Lo, lo, im amarta betumah chamurah sheken einah osah kiyotei
bah.
When you have a weighty טומאה, tumah. it might be weighty, but
it cannot make, it cannot make more of itself. If something is
an אב הטומאה av ha-tumah and if a person touches it he
becomes טמא. tamei. Okay, but he's not an אב. av Or more
than that, the way רש״י Rashi explains it, the person who touched
the אב הטומאה av ha-tumah or swallowed this dead bird let's say,
he's a ראשון. rishon If he touches another person, the other person
doesn't become a ראשון, rishon, right? A person can't, I need, a
person, a ראשון rishon, can only make something a שני, sheni, and
a person can't become a שני. sheni. Whereas by the טומאה tumah
of foodstuffs, if the food is טמא tamei. and it's a ראשון
rishon. and it touches other food, then it does make other food
טמא. tamei It's a שני, sheni, but it makes other food טמא.
tamei. So a person who got טומאה tumah from a טומאה חמורה
tumah chamurah who's an, who touched an אב av, or swallowed this
thing is a ראשון, rishon cannot make another person טמא. tamei, Whereas
food can make more food טמא. tamei, So that's a pretty strange
comparison because obviously still טומאה חמורה tumah chamurah, is certainly more weighty.
Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this. Okay, בטומאה
חמורה שכן אינה עושה כיוצא בה. betumah chamurah sheken einah osah kiyotei
bah.
So by a weighty טומאה, tumah, it has this sort of weakness
that the person it makes טמא tamei, cannot make another person טמא.
tamei תאמר בטומאה קלה שעושה כיוצא בה. Tomar betumah kallah she'osah kiyotei
bah. Would you say by the טומאה tumah foodstuffs,
the food becomes טמא, tamei. it's a ראשון, rishon it can make
other food טמא, tamei a שני. sheni. So therefore even if we
don't demand מחשבה machshava by the טומאה חמורה, tumah chamurah maybe we'll
demand it by the, by this טומאה קלה, tumah kallah. by the,
by the status of a ראשון. rishon. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei
Abaye, אביי Abaye said back, כל שכן הוא. kol sheken hu. What
do you mean? That's a, that's a כל שכן, kol sheken, it's
an, it's the opposite makes sense. ומה טומאה חמורה, u'mah tumah chamurah,
when you're talking about the heavy טומאה, tumah, meaning the, the thing
you swallowed that's an אב, av דקילה, de'kilah, it has a weakness,
what's its weakness? What you just said, דאינה עושה כיוצא בה, de'einah
osah kiyotei bah,
the person it makes טמא, tamei. the man it makes טמא tamei
doesn't make another man טמא. tamei So that's its weakness, and never,
nevertheless even with that weakness, מטמאה שלא במחשבה, metama shelo bemachshava, it
doesn't require מחשבה machshava even though it has that weakness.
טומאה קלה דחמירה, Tumah kallah de'chamira, the lighter טומאה tumah which is
weightier, which דעושה כיוצא בה, de'osah kiyotei bah, it makes food טמא
tamei. and the food makes other food טמא. tamei. In that case,
אינו דין שמטמאה שלא במחשבה? eino din she'metama shelo bemachshava? If it
has that greater power, so then it should, then it should also,
if it has the power to make food and the food make
other food, then it should be able to do it similarly without
מחשבה. machshava Okay, so that was a very bizarre הוה אמינא, hava
amina, not only because of אביי Abaye's כל שכן, kol sheken, but
because obviously טומאה חמורה tumah chamura, is weightier than טומאה tumah קלה.
Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אלא אמר רב ששת,
Ela amar Rav Sheshet, let's focus on this. This answer is the
more straightforward read of it. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is what
they're saying back to רב יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri.
לא, no. It's true that when you swallow it it doesn't need
מחשבה. machshava אם אמרת בטומאה חמורה, when you swallow it and it's
an אב av you don't need מחשבה, machshava שכן אינה צריכה הכשר.
sheken einah tzerichah hechsher.
Because that also does not require הכשר. hechsher. Normally for something to
be a source of טומאה, tumah. it doesn't need to come in
contact with liquids, it doesn't need to be touched by other stuff,
it itself is a source of טומאה tumah. like a carcass, right,
or a משכב mishkav of a זב zav or a dead, or
a dead body. So that is intrinsically a source of טומאה, tumah
and therefore there are no other requirements. It doesn't need water, it
doesn't need to touch something, so it also doesn't need מחשבה machshava
by virtue of what it itself is, it is a source of
טומאה. tumah. So that we understand why it doesn't need מחשבה. machshavah
One minute. תאמר בטומאה קלה שצריכה הכשר, Tomar betumah kallah she'tzerichah hechsher,
but when it comes by the טומאה tumah of foodstuffs, to receive
טומאה tumah elsewhere, they need contact with water, they need to touch
something else, so they also need to be defined as food. So
therefore you can't make a קל וחומר, right? So רב יוחנן בן
נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is saying I'm going to tell you
why this bird becomes a ראשון rishon without מחשבה. Because if it
could be an אב av without מחשבה, it could be a ראשון
rishon. without מחשבה. And the Rabbis' response back is very simple. It
says, excuse me, each category has a separate הלכות. halachot. For an
אב הטומאה, av ha-tumah it's an אב av. by virtue of what
it itself is. You don't need הכשר, hechsher, you don't need to
touch something, you don't need מחשבה. It's a dead carcass, it's מטמא,
metamei end of story. To receive טומאה, tumah you need other criteria.
You need liquid, you need to touch something, and you need to
be defined as food, which means you need מחשבה. So don't make
some קל וחומר. Okay, very simple answer. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says, the גמרא Gemara is still not fully satisfied. The גמרא
Gemara says like this.
וצריכה הכשר? ve'tzerichah hechsher? One minute. Does this dead bird require הכשר?
hechsher? והתנן, Ve'hatnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, right, and we
said this yesterday, שלושה דברים נאמרו בנבלת עוף טהור. Shloshah devarim ne'emru
benivilat of tahor. There are three things that were said, actually it's
remember yesterday it's 13, שלושה עשר דברים נאמרו בנבלת עוף טהור. shloshah
asar devarim ne'emru benivilat of tahor.
We're only going to quote three of them though now. Anyway, thirteen
things were said about the carcass of a dead bird. צריכה מחשבה,
Tzerichah machshava, you need to plan to eat it if you want
it... And it does not need to come in contact with liquid.
Remember we said this yesterday, that the same way because this thing
eventually will can be an אב הטומאה, av ha-tumah it doesn't need
to contact with liquid, it doesn't need to touch something else, once
it's defined as food, it automatically becomes טמא tamei as a ראשון.
rishon, So the גמרא Gemara is saying, so if you admit that
it doesn't need הכשר hechshur in this one case, it shouldn't require
מחשבה because you already admitting that we lower the criteria here and
it doesn't require הכשר. hechshur. So let it not require intention to
treat it as food. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So
the גמרא Gemara is first going to try to get out of
it.
הכשר שרץ לא בעי הכשר מים בעי. Hechshur sheretz lo ba-ei hechshur
mayim ba-ei. It might not require הכשר hechshur of a שרץ, sheretz,
funny phrase, but what it means is it might not require touching
a dead animal, it might not require conducting the טומאה tumah, from
the outside because it itself is a source of טומאה, tumah but
it does require coming in contact with liquid. And the same way
it requires coming in contact with liquid to define it as food,
it requires מחשבה to define it as food. Problem is that isn't
true. So let's take a look. But that's what I told you
yesterday. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't realize that yet. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says.
The גמרא Gemara, says one minute, מאי שנא הכשר שרץ דלא בעי,
mai shena hechshur sheretz de-lo ba-ei, what's different that you said that
this thing, this dead carcass, unlike other foodstuff, does not need to
come in contact with, you know, a dead rodent? It does not
need to conduct the טומאה tumah from the outside.
So דתנא דבי רבי ישמאל, de-tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, like Rabbi Yishmael
taught, הכשר מים נמי לא תיבעי. hechshur mayim nami lo tibei. So
it also shouldn't require coming in contact with liquid כדתנא דבי רבי
ישמאל, ki-detana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, like Rabbi Yishmael taught. What is this
teaching of Rabbi Yishmael? דתנא דבי רבי ישמאל, De-tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael,
we taught in the house of Rabbi Yishmael, על כל זרע זרוע
אשר יזרע. al kol zera zerua asher yizarea. This is the verse
where we learn that foods only conduct טומאה tumah after they've been
in contact with liquid. On every seed that will be planted, that
shall be planted. So that's a pretty, it seems to be a
little repetitive. So מה זרעים שאין סופן לטמא טומאה חמורה צריכים הכשר.
ma zraim she-ein sofan letamei tumah chamura tzrichim hechshur. This is what
Rabbi Yishmael says. The emphasis of זרע זרוע zera zerua is telling
you it has to be like seeds. Seeds will never themselves be
a source of טומאה. tumah, You can never get a seed that's
a source of טומאה. tumah, You can't get טומאה tumah from something
that was never living, that wasn't animal-like. So therefore seeds will never
be a source of טומאה. tumah. In those cases, that's when the
תורה Torah says they need to come in contact with liquid. אף
כל שאין סופו לטמא טומאה חמורה צריכים הכשר. af kol she-ein sofo
letamei tumah chamura tzrichim hechshur. So therefore anything that will never be
a source of טומאה requires contact with liquid to become susceptible. יצתה
נבלת עוף טהור, Yatzta nivlat of tehor,
excluding the case of a carcass of a dead bird, kosher bird,
שסופה לטמא טומאה חמורה, she-sofa letamei tumah chamura, which will eventually be
an אב הטומאה av ha-tumah when you swallow it. In that case,
שאין צריכה הכשר, she-ein tzricha hechshur, does not require הכשר. hechshur. And
here it's very clear that that applies to the case of the
liquids because it's based on a verse that says אשר יבא מים
על זרע, asher yavo mayim al zera, right? That water comes in
contact with the seeds. So it says, look, basically
I get your point. Your point is the Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
is saying, look, as an אב av הטומאה it doesn't need to
think of it as food, so to conduct טומאה from itself it
doesn't need to be food, doesn't need מחשבה. The answer back is
no, no, no. טומאת אוכלין, tummat ochlin, foodstuff has greater criteria. It
needs הכשר, hechshur, it needs to conduct טומאה from the outside, so
it also needs to be defined as food. So the answer is
yeah, but this טומאת אוכלין, tummat ochlin, foodstuff doesn't have those criteria.
It doesn't require liquid, it doesn't require being touched from the outside,
it shouldn't require being defined as food. So that's a pretty strong
argument. So let's see.
Wait, kosher. Right, right.
Kosher, not non-kosher. Non-kosher birds don't cause טומאה, dead birds.
Kosher animals, נבלה, neveila, you know, like cows or whatever and mammals
and even
in the way was a non-kosher.
No, it was a kosher, kosher. Yeah. The גמרא Gemara had a
problem yesterday, oh, how could you say it's a tamei bird that's
non-kosher, and explained it was kosher and so on. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava,
here, ואי תימא רב פפא, ve-i teima Rav Pappa, so rather Rava
and some say Rav Pappa said, שום טומאה חמורה בעולם שום טומאה
קלה בעולם. shum tumah chamura ba-olam shum tumah kala ba-olam. We're not
talking about this specific case. We're talking about the generic category. The
generic category of אב av הטומאה never requires הכשר, hechshur, never requires
touching from the outside, never requires מחשבה. That's the generic category of
an אב הטומאה by virtue of what it is, it's an אב
הטומאה end of story. The generic category of טומאת אוכלין tummat ochlin
requires definition and has criteria. It has to come in contact with
water, it has to conduct the טומאה from the outside, and it
has to be defined as foodstuff. So even though, so Rabbi, the
argument is even though in this case we don't require הכשר, hechshur,
it's still fundamentally in this other category, and the one thing that
we have not waived is the requirement for מחשבה to be defined
as foodstuff. So that's how the debate boils down. So this was
all so far I'm going to tell you. So we have this
weird הלכה halacha that if something is eventually going to be a
טומאה חמורה, then it essentially is מטמא metamei itself, becomes a ראשון
without touching anything from the outside, it does assuming it's a food,
it can be edible, that it's מטמא itself without any contact from
the outside, without הכשר מים, hechsher mayim, without liquid, and the debate
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan בן נורי and the רבנן Rabbanan is
do we also waive the requirement of מחשבה, of intending to treat
it as food? Or do we say, because you could obviously say,
look, if it's a dead carcass that nobody will eat, it only
is becoming טמא tamei. by virtue of being food, only food can
become טמא. tamei, Garbage doesn't become טמא. tamei, So maybe it doesn't
require water or touching something else, but the basic definition of its
identity is food and that's what the רבנן Rabbanan say. That we're
not willing to waive and you still need מחשבה. ורבי יוחנן בן
נורי V'Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says, I'm sorry, if you waive the
other two, you waive that one. If it's edible theoretically, whether you
planned on eating it or whether normal people would eat it doesn't
matter, that is it, it doesn't require מחשבה and it becomes טמא
tamei. without any criteria by essentially it's מטמא itself and becomes a
ראשון.
ורבי יוחנן בן נורי חנניה בן נורי.
Yeah, well that's the debate. Do we waive we waive two out
of the three criteria, do we waive the third one?
Yes, this is for a carcass of a kosher bird. Right. How
about a carcass of a kosher mammal?
Well then that is already a נבלה nevelah and there's no need
to make it into a food טומאה because it already is an
אב. It's an אב whether you
eat it or not.
Right, the only reason it's interesting by a carcass of a dead
bird is if you touch a carcass of a dead bird, it's
not טמא. tamei It functions as an אב when it's swallowed. So
then we can analyze what is its function when you touch a
food to it without it being swallowed, will that conduct טומאה from
it? That's why that becomes an interesting question.
If you plan to eat it.
As you plan to feed it to a non-Jew, hopefully you're not
eating it, it's not kosher. Right, well you can touch it. Actually
you won't be טמא, tamei it's a ראשון, won't make you טמא,
tamei but you can touch if you touch other food to it.
Okay. All right. Now thankfully we end that discussion, which was a
little complicated. And now we get back to the larger issue of
does מחשבה work when something is attached or alive to treat it
as food for the purposes of טומאת אוכלין. tumat ochlin. So that
was the original statement of רבי יוחנן.
The cow, he viewed as steaks, remember?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So that was the position of רבי יוחנן, that
when something is attached, and then the גמרא Gemorah... compared it to
when something is alive, which gets us into the סוגיא sugya of
birds, your מחשבה doesn't matter yet because it's not yet able to
become טמא. tamei So let's see where the גמרא Gemorah. goes with
this. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says רבא, Rava, ומודי רבי יוחנן,
umodei Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן would agree לעניין מעשר le'inyan ma'aser when
it comes to מעשר ma'aser דמחשבה חיבור demachshava chibbur שמה מחשבה shama
machshava that intention to eat it counts even while it's attached. Remember,
one of the criteria for מעשר, ma'aser, and we're going to see
how this is going to tie back to our first משנה, mishna,
because our משנה mishna said anything that's מעשר ma'aser has טומאת tumat
foodstuff because it automatically is defined it has to be food in
order to be מעשר. ma'aser. So if he's going to say so
when if you have something that's growing that's questionable, is it animal
food or human food? If you intend to treat it as human
food, it might not be sufficient מחשבה for purposes of טומאה, but
it is sufficient מחשבה for purposes of מעשר. ma'aser. And now when
you harvest it, you're חייב chayav for מעשר. ma'aser. Of course there's
going to be a problem here that you might anticipate because now
we're going to get something that could be חייב chayav in מעשר
ma'aser without being considered food for the laws of טומאה וטהרה. tumah
v'taharah. But that's the argument, that when it comes to defining it
as food for מעשר, ma'aser, your intention even while it's growing still
works. אמר רבא מנא אמינא לה, Amar Rava mana amina lah, where
did I get this idea from that he would distinguish מעשר ma'aser
from everything else? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה: mishna: השאה
והאזוב והקורנית שבחצר. Hasha'ah v'ha'ezov v'hakornit shebechatzer. So these are different types
of things, I looked every one of them up and I can't
tell well I know אזוב ezov is hyssop, שאה, sha'ah, I forget
what these are, one of them was, I don't know, does somebody
have an English? What? Thyme, okay.
They call pennyroyal and savory.
Okay, savory. Savory and thyme, I guess
those were the two.
Spices, right. Herbs, right. Well, okay. So thyme and savory and various
types of things שבחצר shebechatzer are growing in your yard, not in
the field. What?
קורנית Kornit is is
is is also another type of spice? Yes, it's a variety.
Yeah, one of these is thyme, the other is savory. Okay, anyway,
savory is an actual name of a spice, not just an adjective.
Anyway, they're growing in your yard. Okay, presumably if they were growing
out in the field, it would be more obvious, let's say they
would be animal food, maybe they're growing in your yard, maybe they
just sprouted up on their own, I know you accidentally dropped some
seeds, or anyway there's maybe a greater likelihood you'll harvest you'll take
a few into the house and use it for human food. So
let's take a look. They're grown in your yard. אם היו נשמרים,
Im hayu nishmarim, if you were guarding them, meaning they weren't just
growing wild, you were guarding them and you were protecting them because
you wanted actually to harvest to cut them and use them, חייב,
chayav, then they're obligated in מעשר. ma'aser. Okay, because if you remember,
one of the criteria for מעשר ma'aser is that it has to
be נשמר, nishmar, it can't be הפקר, hefker, it can't just lay
out, who cares, it grew wild, I don't care about it. You
have to be guarding it and protecting it and wanting to actually
harvest it. Okay, so that's what it says. Now, it seems that
the emphasis of נשמר nishmar is exactly what I said, that there
are times where people might just it might be wild and don't
care, and this is telling you if you make it נשמר, nishmar,
then it's obligated because it's not הפקר, hefker, because it's guarded. But
the גמרא Gemara understands that no, that maybe the reason we said
נשמר nishmar here is maybe because these things sometimes are for animal
food, and the emphasis here is not just that it's not הפקר...
hefker... The emphasis here is that you're intending to eat it, you're
intending to use it as human food. That's how the גמרא Gemara
initially reads this. So let's take a look. היכי דמי, Heichi dami,
what's the case? אילימא דזרעינהו מתחילה לאדם, Ileima d'zar'inhu mitchila l'adam, if
you planted them intentionally for your own purposes, צריכא למימר, tzricha l'meimar,
of course it's obligated. Why do you have to say נשמר? nishmar?
And obviously then also presumably you'd also be watching it yourself. I
mean that would go without saying, you're planting it, you're intending to
use it. So אלא לאו דזרעינהו מתחילה לבהמה, ela lav d'zar'inhu mitchila
l'behema, it must be the scenario is and why maybe it's not
considered נשמר nishmar initially, because maybe you planted it for animals. ותני,
V'tani, and then it says, אופני אם היו נשמרים חייבים, ofni im
hayu nishmarim chayavim, only if you then are watching it now for
your sake to use it for human spices, now is it obligated.
So it's choosing to read נשמר nishmar meaning that you are now
choosing to use them for human purposes.
Meaning you always planted it intentionally,
just you changed your mind. Now that's a funny way of framing
the case which the גמרא Gemara is going to reject, but that's
how it's reading this משנה. mishnah. So you see once you make
your mind to use it, it becomes obligated in מעשר ma'aser and
your intention even when it's growing is significant. So אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, no. הכא בחצר שאינה משתמרת עסקינן. Hacha bechatzer she'eina
mishtameret askinan.
No, that's not the case and you gotta admit רב אשי Rav
Ashi is really the most obvious read of this משנה. mishnah. It's
talking about if they just sprouted on their own in your yard.
וסתמא לאדם קאי, V'stama l'adam kai, and it's not about making it
human food. We would assume these spices are considered food are you
know are going to be used by humans. So that's not the
that's not the issue. The issue isn't human versus animal food. What's
the issue? The issue is whether it's נשמר nishmar or הפקר. hefker.
והכי קאמר, V'hachi ka'amar, this is what it's saying. אם חצר משמרת
פירותיה, Im chatzer mshameret peiroteha, if in your yard it protects against
you know your the things that are growing are protected, then חייבין
chayavin then they're obligated because it's נשמר. nishmar. ואם לאו, V'im lav,
if things that grow in your yard are not protected, either you
don't care or it's just people naturally walk through your yard and
pick the stuff as randomly growing. The reality is that they're not
protected, then פטורים pturim they're exempt. So basically it's a much it's
a very different point. It's not about human versus animal. It's say
you got some wild stuff that's growing in your yard, is that
considered נשמר nishmar or הפקר? hefker? So it depends, if your your
yard is protected, if you're protecting them, it's נשמר. nishmar. Otherwise, even
though they could be used as human foods and the people are
going to walk through your yard and pick them without permission or
with or without permission whatever are going to use them, they're human
food but they're not נשמר nishmar and therefore they're
exempt. מכדי שיתילי דלעא, Michdi shitilei d'la'a, you know that some types
of things you know that I don't know I mean I think
it's just a good good graphic example of נשמר nishmar versus הפקר.
hefker. הפקר Hefker doesn't just you know you could basically have stuff
in your yard and generally you don't want people trampling through your
yard but what about the various things grow that you don't really
care about so much.
There's nothing so special about שיתילי דלעא. shitilei d'la'a. No I don't.
Yeah I just think that those are like common cases right. Exactly
which might be why the גמרא Gemara, initially tried to read it
about human versus animal because if it's about how edible it is
then it might be specific to the type of מין. min. If
it's just to give you like a good illustration of example of
נשמר nishmar things that grow wild it depends on whether you're protecting
them or not protecting them then it didn't have to be a
specific you know then it could have been a little more generic.
So that could be why the גמרא Gemara thought otherwise. Okay so
let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues to prove
try to argue this case about מעשר. ma'aser. So אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, wait did I skip a line? Yeah. אמתיב רב אשי. Amtiv
Rav Ashi. רב אשי Rav Ashi asked on רבא's Rava argument. כל
שחייב במעשר, Kol shechayav b'ma'aser, our משנה, mishnah, anything obligated in מעשר
ma'aser מטמא טומאת אוכלין mitamei tumat ochlin is considered
a foodstuff. It wouldn't be חייב במעשר chayav b'ma'aser if it wasn't
food and cannot become טמא as food. ואי איתא, V'i ita, if
what you're saying is correct that מחשבה works for מעשר ma'aser when
it's growing but not for food. האיכא הני דחייבין במעשר ואין מטמאין
טומאת אוכלין? Ha'ika hanei d'chayavin b'ma'aser v'ein mitamin tumat ochlin? How about
I'll give you an example that goes against the משנה. mishnah. You've
got stuff growing that normally would be animal food or you know
it's sort of in this middle category and as it's growing you're
intending to use it as human food. Then according to you it's
not considered food for the purposes of טומאה, right? Obviously while it's
growing not but even after you cut it it's not yet considered
food for the purposes of טומאה because your intention was when it
was growing and that doesn't work for טומאה. But it is considered
food for the purposes of מעשר ma'aser because you said that for
מעשר ma'aser even when it's growing your intention matters. So that goes
against our משנה. mishnah. Something is considered food for מעשר ma'aser and
not considered food for foodstuff. So that's a pretty good proof against
רבא. Rava. Let's see what the answer back is. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, רבא Rava would say back. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is
how you read it. כל מין שחייב במעשר מטמא טומאת אוכלין. Kol
min shechayav b'ma'aser mitamei tumat ochlin. We don't mean that there can't
be a case circumstances where something is one without the other. What
we mean is any type any you know מין min what's the
word species of food that is in the category of of of
מעשר ma'aser is in the category to become טמא as foodstuff. It
doesn't mean at the exact moment
it's חייב במעשר chayav b'ma'aser it's חייב chayav as food. In this
case your מחשבה made it חייב במעשר chayav b'ma'aser and it's not
yet טמא as food until you have that intention after it's harvested
after it's cut. But it's the type of it's the species that
matter. Any species that's חייב במעשר chayav b'maaser will be able to
become טמא as foodstuff. Okay, even though here in these circumstances it
is not yet that way, because your intention was when it was
growing. So let's take a look. הכי נמי מסתברא. Hachi nami mistabra.
You know, that makes sense that our Mishnah is talking about species
and not about particular
circumstances. Why? לדתני סיפא, Lidktanei seifa, we taught at the end—not really
at the end of that Mishnah, it's like the end of however
you divide the Mishnah, but a Mishnah we're about to read when
we turn the page. What does the next Mishnah say? כל שחייב
בראשית הגז חייב במתנות. Kol shechayav b'reishit hagez chayav b'matanot. Anything that's
obligated in the first shearings, right, when you shear your sheep, and
you, there's a certain number of sheep and a certain amount you
shear, you give a certain amount of those shearings to the כהן.
Kohen. So if it's in that category, חייב במתנות, chayav b'matanot, then
when you slaughter, you also have to give the gifts to the
כהן. Kohen. You might remember this from the end of חולין, Chullin,
זרוע ולחיים וקיבה, Zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva, right, the arm, the cheek, the
maw, and so on. So if it's in, if you're going to
give the shearings, you're going to give those gifts. ויש שחייב במתנות
ואין חייב בראשית הגז. V'yesh shechayav b'matanot v'ein chayav b'reishit hagez. There
are things that you give the מתנות matanot and you don't give
ראשית הגז. reishit hagez. Can you think what things you give gifts
and you don't give the shearings? It's like so obvious you might
not realize it.
What? The things that are like true, the other מתנות. matanot.
No, no, no, but you know, but you give the gifts, מתנות
matanot meaning זרוע ולחיים וקיבה. zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva. The things you give
זרוע ולחיים וקיבה zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva you don't give shearings.
The קרבנות? Korbanot? What? You don't... you're thinking too hard.
Cows! Cows! זרוע ולחיים וקיבה Zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva
and you don't give
shearings, right. Sometimes, it's like this, there's a joke which says, what
do you call a Jewish baby that doesn't have a ברית? bris?
A girl, a
this, a that, a girl! Okay, anyway.
So alright, anyway, so it says, alright. Okay, so that's the Mishnah.
ואי איתא, V'im itai, if we're talking not just about species, sheep,
cows, different types of food, of vegetables and fruits, we're talking about
circumstances as opposed to species, הא איכא טרפה. ha ika tereifah. Then
there's something that violates this rule, if an animal is a טרפה.
tereifah. דחייבא בראשית הגז, Dechayava b'reishit hagez, you still give the shearings,
your sheep is a טרפה, tereifah, right. The fact that it's a
טרפה tereifah doesn't impact the shearings, shearing is wool. ואינה חייבת במתנות,
V'einah chayava b'matanot, but you don't give the gifts because you're not
giving the gifts of an animal that can't be eaten. Okay. So
therefore you see that this point of this Mishnah is to talk
about species of things, types of things, not circumstances. In a particular
circumstance, it might not be this rule, but in terms of the
species, that's what we're talking about.
But the first part of the Mishnah should be what Mishnah said.
What do you mean?
One by two, I by one, I...
Well, that's a good point. That is more, that is not so
much about species as it is about circumstances, but the גמרא, yeah,
somehow the גמרא isn't being bothered by that. That's a good point.
אמר רבינא הא מני רבי שמעון היא. Amar Ravina, ha mani Rabbi
Shimon hi. Now, that's not a counterproof. I could say that that's
even that's not an exception. Why? Maybe it's going according to Rabbi
Shimon. דתנן, D'tenan, we talk, ותניא ברייתא, v'tanya baraita, Rabbi Shimon פוטר
poter the טרפה tereifah from ראשית הגז. reishit hagez. Rabbi Shimon says
that a טרפה tereifah also the same way it doesn't give the
מתנות, matanot, also you don't give the ראשית הגז, reishit hagez, the
shearings from a sheep that's a טרפה. tereifah. So you have not
proved it. I would argue that the Mishnah is not limiting itself
to these rules by species, maybe it even applies to cases of
circumstances. So we still don't know the answer to that when the
Mishnah says, if in A it's B, but B not A, does
that mean all the time or just species that are in A
are necessarily in B and so on? And that's the question about
the argument that something could be food because of מחשבה based on
מעשר maaser without being that way for טומאת אוכלין. tumas ochlin. Okay,
so let's take a look. We're not done. אמר רב אשי תא
שמע, Amar Rav Ashi, tasha, come and hear. אמר רב שימי בר
חייא המפקיר כרמו והשכים בבוקר ובצרו. Amar Rav Shimi bar Chiya, hamafkir
karmo, v'hishkim baboker u'vtzaro. You at night you said, my vineyard is
completely הפקר. hefker. And then or maybe the vines, I don't know
if you actually the land, and then you got up the next
morning and before anybody heard of your little announcement that you made
at midnight, you got up at 6:00 AM and you harvested your
vineyard. Now, why would you bother doing something? Either you changed your
mind or maybe it gets you out of תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros
because once something is הפקר, hefker, even if it's reclaimed, it's exempt
from תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. So how far, how much does this
exempt you from? חייב, Chayav, so no, you still are חייב chayav
the פרט peret and עוללות olelot and שכחה shichechah and פאה. peah.
You're חייב chayav in פרט peret and עוללות olelot which are different
types of gleanings of the grapes of like certainly unripe clusters, unformed
clusters, or droppings of the, of the grapes and שכחה shichechah what
you forgot and פאה peah the corner. So all of the gifts
to the poor you're obligated. This little trick didn't help you. ופטור
מן המעשרות. U'patur min hamaasros. You are exempt from מעשרות. maasros. That's
a הלכה we learn it out from the fact that the פסוק
pasuk says תעזב לעני ולגר תעזב אתם ta'azov l'ani v'lager ta'azov otan
and it repeats תעזב אתם ta'azov otan leave them, leave them by
the gifts to the poor, that even in this trick case you
have to leave it. But the trick does work, not for the
gifts to the poor, but for תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. It's actually
interesting for a moment to think about the difference
because one difference could be just the Torah is more insistent that
you don't cheat out the poor as opposed to מעשרות maasros which
maybe it has more technical requirements, but another possible difference also... It
would be that
by the מעשר maaser. *Maiser*, although it's true that the gifts to
the poor really only apply in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*,
it has a little less to do with the קדושה *Kedusha* of
the פירות *Peiros*, you know, like the קדושת הארץ *Kedushas Ha'aretz*. And
if you don't give the gifts to the poor, so your fruit
isn't טבל *Tevel*, whereas by תרומות ומעשרות Trumos u'Ma'asros *Trumos U'Maisros*, it's
more of a sense of the קדושה *Kedusha* of the ארץ *Aretz*,
the קדושה *Kedusha* of the פירות *Peiros*. If you don't give it,
your fruit is טבל *Tevel*, so it's much more about the status
issue. So maybe once that status is interrupted, it's הפקר hefker. *Hefker*
even for a few hours and it loses its status and its
identity. Even in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. I understand, but if one
of the criteria for the חיוב *Chiyuv* of תרומות ומעשרות Trumos u'Ma'asros?
*Trumos U'Maisros* is not הפקר hefker *Hefker*, then for at least that
hour it lost its status. So it could be that there's also
a conceptual difference here about the nature of gifts to the poor
as opposed to the nature of תרומות ומעשרות Trumos u'Ma'asros *Trumos U'Maisros*
in addition to the idea that it's not nice to cheat the
poor. It's also not nice to cheat out the לוי *Levi*, but
okay, yes. So I declare something הפקר hefker, *Hefker* and before I
wake
up in the morning,
someone else comes and harvests. There you go!
Now is that person required to
give תרומות ומעשרות Trumos u'Ma'asros *Trumos U'Maisros*, to give the gifts to
the poor? Yeah, that is a good question, presumably not because the
real answer is that הפקר *Hefker* is פטור patur *Potur* and the
only point here is that it was practically transferred at that time
and he actually wasn't even the person who raised it. Correct.
I think the answer is no, I think in that case it's
the real case that הפקר *Hefker* is פטור *Potur* and then it
transfers. But here it's only because you re-harvested. But I need to
check, but I'm pretty sure the answer to that is no.
In that case, maybe these obligations are דרבנן drabbanan *Drabanan* rather than
דאורייתא *Deoraissa*?
No, the גמרא *Gemara* learns it out from the פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk*
of תעזוב *Taazov* and very much insists that it's דאורייתא *Deoraissa*. Wow.
Yeah. But it is a good question if somebody else harvests. But
there it's different also because A, in this case it's obviously just
a trick, it's not really interrupted by a different ownership, and also
in your scenario the person who now owns it is not the
person in whose yard it grew. So that's a general question about
לקוח *Lakwach* and when things transfer ownership even without being הפקר *Hefker*,
right? If I have my whole field standing with grain and I
sell it to you, although there it's a little different because there
it's a question when would it reach שליש *Shlish*. Anyway, it's a
good question, I'd have to double-check that. Okay, so let's see where
the גמרא *Gemara* goes with it.
Can you declare something הפקר *Hefker* just by thinking about it?
No. So that's a good point too. There's a question about what
is the criteria for הפקר *Hefker*. According to a גמרא נדרים *Gemara
Nedarim* or whatever, it seems like you need to do it in
front of three people. So of course if you're doing it in
front of three people, alright, you know, so then obviously you're taking
a bit of a risk here that it's still going to be,
or maybe the three people are the three people living in your
house and they're under strict orders not to tell anybody else, I
don't
know. But okay. Alright, let's take a look where the גמרא *Gemara*
goes with it. So now what do we have? Now we have
this grain that you made הפקר *Hefker* and you repossessed in the
next morning. And what do we say? We say that it is
חייב chayav *Chayav* in פאה peah?
*Peah* and פטור *Potur* from מעשר maaser. *Maaser*. But that violates a
rule we had yesterday. דתנן *Detnan*, didn't we learn in the משנה
Mishna, *Mishna* yesterday, כל שחייב בפאה חייב chayav במעשר *Kol She'chayav B'Peah
Chayav B'Maaser*, if it's obligated in פאה peah. *Peah* it's obligated in
מעשר maaser. *Maaser*? And this is something that's obligated in פאה peah
*Peah* and פטור *Potur* from מעשר maaser, *Maaser* because of this trick
you did. So it violates the rule. אלא לאו שמע מינה מין
קתני שמע מינה *Ella Lav Shma Mina Min Katani Shma Mina*. You
see we're talking about species of food, species of animals that are
in one category they're in the other. Not about circumstances. And there
can be a circumstance of one type of a species which it's
true is obligated in both, but in this circumstance it's only obligated
in פאה peah *Peah* not מעשר maaser. *Maaser*. Similarly by the case
of having מחשבה *Machshava* by this growing, these growing spices, in that
circumstance it could be that it's in the category of מעשר maaser,
*Maaser* and not in the category of טומאת אוכלין tumas ochlin *Tumas
Ochlin*. So that is a good proof and the גמרא *Gemara* is
satisfied. Now we move on to yet another case which again we're
going to bring in the relevance of our משנה Mishna *Mishna* of
if it's in one category it's got to be in the other.
תנן התם *Tnan Hasam*.
So we're just saying we just defended רבא *Rava*, doesn't necessarily mean
we proved רבא *Rava*?
We defended רבא *Rava*, right. רבא *Rava* hasn't proved his point, correct.
There's no proof to רבא *Rava*, but we've said that at least
it's a viable claim. תנן התם *Tnan Hasam*. Right, we taught over
there in פאה peah, *Peah*. מודים חכמים לרבי עקיבא *Modim Chachamim L'Rabbi
Akiva*. Now there's a debate of the חכמים *Chachamim* and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*. What happens if you sort of harvest your
field in patchwork? So basically remember we discussed yesterday questions about whether
you consider something one field or multiple fields, do you give פאה
peah. *Peah* in each section or from the whole. Well what happens
if you sort of, you know, took first of all some grain
from here and took a patch over here and a patch over
here? Does that now make your field considered to be what's left
different sections or is it still one big field, one פאה peah.
*Peah* or multiple? So there's a debate of the חכמים *Chachamim* and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*. But now we're going to say
there's a case that they all agree. מודים חכמים לרבי עקיבא *Modim
Chachamim L'Rabbi Akiva*, the חכמים *Chachamim* agree to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
*Rabbi Akiva*, בזורע שבת או חרדל *B'zoreia Sheves O Chardal*, if you
plant dill or mustard, בשנים ושלשה מקומות *B'shnayim U'shlosha Mekomos*, in two
or three places, שנותן פאה peah מכל אחד ואחד *She'nosen Peah Mi'kol
Echad V'Echad*, then it's not considered one unit of dill, one unit
of mustard. Apparently the custom was where you don't plant a lot
of mustard together. You have a big field then you plant different
small little areas of dill and mustard. I don't know why that
was the practice, that was the practice. So in that case as
opposed to
the case... with what you're left with. But if from the outset
you plant things in little different little sections, so then it's not
one big mustard harvest, each little section is considered its own mini
field and you leave a separate פאה peah, for each one.
Okay. Is there a minimum for פאה?
peah Yeah, so a tiny amount, there's no real definition of what's
פאה.
peah, Okay, hear that every
morning, אלו דברים שאין להם שיעור. eilu devarim she'ein lahem shiur.
No, they don't actually give one?
No.
There's a rabbinic minimum for תרומה, truma, but for פאה peah, I'm
trying to remember... not that I remember. But anyway, obviously it does
make a difference. Well, it's just a point about you're about... I
mean, it's not a question about how much money are you out,
but it is a question about how you harvest.
Do you leave a little section or... I know, like, you can
take this leaf over over here. Right. No, פאה peah, is for
the poor, like
how does the poor know that you're done or not?
Here, there, there, there, there. It's where it's left.
Yeah, but I assume your question was, how do they know that
you've not yet finished?
Right, that, and also like how do they know how much of
it is פאה, peah, because if I can just leave whatever I
want.
Right. Right, I don't know, maybe you put out a flag. I
really have no idea. I really have no idea. All right. So
now the גמרא says והשבת שמתחייבת בפאה. vehashaves shemitchayeves bepeah. Now we're
going to draw conclusions from this. So we see from here שבת
שמתחייבת בפאה, shaves shemitchayeves bepeah, dill is obligated in פאה. peah? That's
the only reason we quoted this משנה, Mishna not for the question
of one field or multiple fields, but it's clear from this משנה
Mishna, that dill is obligated in פאה. Pe'ah ומתחייבת במעשר. umitchayeves bemaaser.
So therefore based on our rule, which now we've established also applies
to species, any species that's חייב chayav in פאה is חייב chayav
in מעשר. maaser. So if dill is פאה, dill is מעשר. maaser,
Fine. דתנן כל שחייב בפאה חייב במעשר, desnan kol shechayav bepeah chayav
bemaaser, like our משנה mishna. teaches, it's פאה and
מעשר. maaser ומי דחייבת במעשר, umi dechayaves bemaaser, now since dill is
obligated in מעשר, maaser, מטמאה טומאת אוכלין. metamei tumas ochlin. So now
we're going through all the cases of the משנה, mishnah, right? Since
it's פאה, it's מעשר. Since it's מעשר, it can become טמאי tamei
as foodstuff. So once we find that dill is פאה, we know
that dill is obligated in מעשר. Once obligated in מעשר, anything in
מעשר is טמאי tamei as foodstuff. So dill can be טמאי tamei
as foodstuff. All seems like a very straightforward argument. אלמא כל מילי
דעביד לטעמא מטמא טומאת אוכלין. alma kol mili deavid letaama metamei tumas
ochlin. Now this teaches an important principle: that spices are טמאי tamei
as foodstuff, right? Because you... that's a good question. Do you consider
a spice a food? You don't eat it directly. Now תוספות by
the way points out that there are two types of spices. There's
onions and garlic, which you do eat directly. They're basically vegetables, but
they also are very much used as spice. So those things clearly
are food. But things that are fundamentally just to add spice and
aren't really eaten directly, are they considered food or not? So if
it's in פאה, it's in מעשר, it's in foodstuff, presumably this is
all considered food, even spices, and it causes... it can become טמאי
tamei as foodstuff. Okay, that seems to make sense, but now we
have...
that should have been the assumption. Right, I mean all these things
we've been talking about.
I mean, right, the thyme and whatever, right, it could have brought
us from there. This is missing the focusing on the case of
the dill, but that's correct. But now we have a question because
the reason we have a question is because the contrast... well let's
take a look. Okay. דהאי שבת לטעמא עבידי, dehai shaves letaama avidi,
this dill, dill was a spice. רמינהי, raminhu, I'll ask a contradiction.
הכושת והחימום וראשי בשמים והטאה והחילפה והפלפלין וחלת חריע, hakoshos vehachimum veroshei
besamim vehata'ah vehachilfah vehapilpelin vechalas charia, all these different types of spices,
somebody will help me what that list is because I looked it
up and I forgot it. I don't remember any of those. What
was the first one? Pennyroyal, shoteh peppers, and safflower.
And pepper doesn't mean the big red or green. No, no, no,
it means black pepper, whatever. Okay, I think you skipped some. There
was הכושת, hakoshos, pyrethrum, and herbs.
Pyrethrum is a chrysanthemum. Okay, so now you know. Okay, anyway. All
of these various spices, נלקחין בכסף מעשר. nilkachin bekesef maaser.
You can buy with מעשר שני maaser sheni money. Okay, because they're
food. So so far that's consistent.
ואין מטמאין טומאת אוכלין, ve'ein mitam'in tumas ochlin, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei
Rabbi Akiva. And רבי עקיבא says but אע"פ, af al pi, they're
not considered food, so maybe for מעשר שני maaser sheni money it's
enough to use them... we haven't discussed what you need for מעשר
שני, maaser sheni, but maybe for מעשר שני maaser sheni is enough
that they can be a spice to food, but for טומאת אוכלין
it has to be real food and these aren't real food. That's
what רבי עקיבא says. אמרו לו לרבי יוחנן בן נורי, amru lo
leRabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, רבי יוחנן בן נורי says to him: make
up your mind. אם נלקחין בכסף מעשר, im nilkachin bekesef maaser, if
you can use מעשר שני maaser sheni money for it, מפני מה
אין מטמאין טומאת אוכלין, mipnei mah ein mitam'in tumas ochlin, then they're
food, then they... then why shouldn't they become טמאי tamei as foodstuff?
ואם אין מטמאין, ve'im ein mitam'in, if they're not טמאי tamei as
foodstuff, אף הם לא ילקחו בכסף מעשר, af hem lo yilkechu bekesef
maaser, then they're not food, you can't buy it with מעשר שני
maaser sheni money. So okay, so he says they are totally linked.
So which way does it go? ואמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי, ve'amar
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, רבי יוחנן בן נורי says: נמנו וגמרו, nimnu
vegamru, we took a vote and we concluded שאין נלקחין בכסף מעשר
ואין מטמאין טומאת אוכלין, she'ein nilkachin bekesef maaser ve'ein mitam'in tumas ochlin,
that spices are not food. You can't use your מעשר שני maaser
sheni money for it, they're not טמאי tamei as food. Spices, spices
are not food. Now we've got a question. But presumably רבי עקיבא
was outvoted because הלכה כרבי עקיבא מחבירו ולא מחביריו. halacha keRabbi Akiva
mechaveiro velo mechaveirav. Now we've got a problem. Spices aren't foodstuff and
we just saw here that dill is... you're חייב in פאה, and
as Dovid pointed out, we pointed out earlier that the other types
of stuff, what was it, thyme and whatever, is savory, was that
פאה? Yeah, that was מעשר *maaser*. Okay, so now we have spices
that are, but now we're saying here that spices are not טמא
טומאת אוכלין *tamei tumat ochalin* and they're not bought with מעשר שני
*maaser sheni* and they're not food. So how does it make sense?
So let's see what the גמרא's *Gemara's* answer is. So אמר רב
חסדא *amar Rav Chisda* כי תניא היא *ki tanya hi* when do
we say spices are considered to be פאה *peah* and would presumably
be טמא טומאת אוכלין *tamei tumat ochalin*? בשבת העשויה לקמח *be-shaves ha-asuyah
le-kemach* when we are dealing with dill that is made for קמח
*kemach* like a type of a sourdough which basically means the following:
when you are making a sauce, like if you are making a
dill sauce, then I know my wife's family has this thing where
they do dill and mayonnaise and some other type of stuff that
they use for like, for what do you call it, for like
asparagus, like an asparagus type of a sauce. So if it's a
dill sauce, then fundamentally the identity of the food that you're making,
the sauce, is because of the flavor in it. That flavor, that
makes it a foodstuff. If you are basically cooking, I don't know,
a טשולנט *cholent* or something and you're throwing in a little rosemary
and a little dill, then it's just spicing up the food. It
isn't the food, right? It isn't the food, it's spicing the food.
But if it's actually a sauce, then the spice is the food,
then that actually is the food that's being made is about the
spice and then it does count as a foodstuff. So we will
have to now say that all the cases that we said that
dill and thyme and savory are מעשר *maaser*, are פאה *peah*, they
would be טמא טומאת אוכלין *tamei tumat ochalin*, but those are only
special cases when you're growing them for the purpose of making some
type of a sauce with them. But if you're growing them just
to be in your kitchen and you sort of put a little
bit in on your salad and whatever, then they would not be
considered food. Okay, so the question is of course what if you
want multi-purpose savory? So let's take a look what the גמרא *Gemara*
says. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אמר רב אשי *amar
Rav Ashi* אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב כהנא *amritah li-shmaata kamei de-Rav Kahana*.
I told over this discussion to רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*. And he
said back to me, לא תימא בשבת העשויה לקמח *lo teima be-shaves
ha-asuyah le-kemach*. Don't say we're talking about dill that is made for
this type of a dip, which means it's a special case, הסתמא
לקדרה *ha-stama le-kdeirah* which means normally it's made for just putting into
your pot and therefore only considered a spice and not a food,
אלא סתם שבת לקמח עשויה *ela stam shaves le-kemach asuyah*. No, the
standard is we assume that it is made for a type of
a dip and this dill is made for a dip and it
is considered food and only in a special case would it not
be that way. How do I know that? דתנן *di-tnan* we taught
in the משנה mishnah, *Mishnah* השבת משנתנה טעם בקדרה *ha-shaves mishe-natnah taam
bi-kdeirah* אין בה משום תרומה ואינה מטמאה טומאת אוכלין *ein bah mishum
trumah ve-einah mitamaat tumat ochalin*. משינתנה *mishe-natnah* excuse me, I'm sorry, משינתנה
*mishe-nitnah* once it gives taste into the pot, so it becomes essentially
part of the pot, then it's only a spice and since it's
only a spice, it's not a תרומה *trumah* problem. If it was
תרומה *trumah* then it's not like, oh my god, I have תרומה
*trumah* in my food. It's only a spice so it loses its
identity, it's no longer a food, and it could not become טמא
*tamei* as foodstuff. So basically once it seasons a pot, it's only
considered a spice and not considered a food. So that makes it
pretty clear that until you used it in this pot, the standard,
it would have been considered a food, right? Only once it was
used as a spice to something else does it lose its identity,
but until that point, it has its identity. So it says ואי
סלקא דעתך סתמא לקדרה *ve-i salka daatach stama le-kdeirah* if you assume
that its normal identity is already assumed that it's going to be
going into a pot, so כי לא נתנה נמי סתמא לקדרה *ki
lo nitnah nami stama le-kdeirah* even before you put it in the
pot, it should not be considered a foodstuff because that's where it's
headed, אלא לאו שמע מינה סתם לקמח עשויה *ela lav shma minah
stam le-kemach asuyah* you see that the assumption is that you're going
to use it for a dip and therefore until you actually have
used it for the pot, it is considered to be a food.
שמע מינה *shma minah* we see that. Now again, the question is
what about other spices? Because as Dov correctly points out, right, just
on the previous we had a case by the case of the
savory and the, you know, the thyme and whatever. Is this a
general statement that anything that's grown as a spice we assume it's
a food because we assume you're going to use it as some
dip until you actually use it to spice something else? Or no?
I mean, you know, maybe it depends, case by case. Some things
maybe are naturally used more for dips, other things are naturally more
used to add a little spice to a pot. So here it
becomes a very important interesting question about the status of spices as
foodstuffs with the נפקא מינה *nafka minah* of פאה *peah*, מעשר *maaser*,
מעשר שני *maaser sheni*, טומאת אוכלין *tumat ochalin*, all these various things
where the גמרא *Gemara* says it really depends on whether it's fundamentally
going to be used to spice something else or whether it's going
to be used to create a type of a sauce or a
dip. Yes. Practically related is to eat, if it is subject to
מעשר *maaser*, wouldn't it also be subject to תרומה *trumah* and therefore
טבל *tevel*? Right, you'd have to take תרומות ומעשרות *trumot u-maasrot* from
them. Right. How do we פסק *pasken* on that? That's a good
question. Like you're right, like in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. Yeah, in
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* you have to worry about תרומות ומעשרות *trumot
u-maasrot* from spices. Yeah. That's a very good question about practically whether
we assume סתם לקדרה *stam le-kdeirah* or not. I would assume the
normal, I don't know, let me see if I could find if
there's some contemporary discussion of that. One would assume that the normal
reality by spices is סתם לקדרה *stam le-kdeirah*. dried spices. Mustards maybe,
you know say make sauce out of it. That's interesting. Yeah, so
maybe that's also true. We think about- we think about dried spices,
right? But the גמרא was presumably talking about everything was fresh here.
So the second question is making a ברכה bracha on them. If
you eat them directly? Yeah. It is- it's already food for you
now, wouldn't you have to make a ברכה? bracha? Yeah, but that
also- but that also- no. If you eat something directly that it's
not the דרך derech to eat it that way, then you make
שהכל shehakol regardless, you know. So but you've got to make a
שהכל. shehakol. Yeah, I mean, as long as you're getting some הנאה,
hana'ah, you're making a שהכל. shehakol. Yeah. So my question is, I
know this has an answer, you know, sometimes we say לא פלוג
lo plug and over here we're getting into like, you know, all
these... Oh wait, I just do want to say one thing though.
There is a question if you just like taste something. Like if
you're making a dish and you just like put something at the
tip of your tongue to taste it, there's a question about whether
that's considered eating or not and whether that requires a ברכה bracha
and other types of הלכות. halachos. But we'll learn that next week.
Yes. Yeah. So sometimes we say לא פלוג lo plug and over
here we're getting into like, you know, all these... you know... well,
it is what it is, right? So, you know, to me it
would seem this would be a great cat- time to say לא
פלוג lo plug because this is- it's confusing enough as it is.
Well, only at a rabbinic level. I mean, a lot of אסטראלי
Istrali says, you know, where- why we're not learning the rest of-
of סדר טהרות, Seder Taharos, why also not learning the גמרא... we're
not going to learn the rest of סדר זרעים Seder Zeraim when
we get to ברכות, Brachos, but a lot of the laws of
תרומות ומעשרות and פאה are all about different types of species and
what are their exact, you know, definitions and are they, you know,
נשמר nishmar and אוכל ochel and are they מחשב לאדם machshav l'adam
or לבהמה l'behema and all these types of cases. So לא פלוג
lo plug is by דרבנן drabbanan laws. Now you could ask, why
didn't the דרבנן just say let's not make all these distinctions and
just say you always give תרומות ומעשרות? Well, first of all, I
would say that makes- I mean, you know, sort of that's the
אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach. איננו בקיאים. einenu b'ki'im. Just מחמיר machmir across the
board. I'm sorry, that's- you see that a lot in אשכנזי פסק
Ashkenazi psak in הלכות נידה, hilchos nidda, in הלכות כשרות, hilchos kashrus,
we'll just be מחמיר machmir across the board rather than make distinctions.
So number one, that leads to a lot of חומרות. chumros. Number
two, here it could also lead to חומרא אתי לידי קולא chumra
asi lidei kula because then you might- maybe you'll take, you know,
תרומות ומעשרות from something that's פטור on something that's חייב and so
on. So but, you know, most- a lot of laws of תרומות
ומעשרות are all about making these types of distinctions. It requires a
lot of knowledge of agriculture, which is maybe also why it makes
our life a lot easier that we're not learning it. Okay, anyway,
let's take a look at, right, at the next משנה. כל שחייב
בראשית הגז, kol shechayav b'reishis hagez, we already saw this, חייב במתנות.
chayav b'matanos. Anything obligated in shearing is obligated in the gift, הזרוע
והלחיים והקיבה, hazroa vehalechayayim vehakeiva, that's ש'. sh. ויש שחייב במתנות ואינו
חייב בראשית הגז, v'yesh shechayav b'matanos v'eino chayav b'reishis hagez, cows. כל
שיש לו ביעור kol sheyesh lo bi'ur or goats also. כל שיש
לו ביעור יש לו שביעית. kol sheyesh lo bi'ur yesh lo shevi'is.
Anything that you have to- to remove out of your house, literally
destroy, apply all the other laws of שביעית shevi'is apply. What are
the laws of שביעית? shevi'is? Number one is that you have to
make them הפקר. Number two is- is that you can't do business
with fruit of שביעית. shevi'is. Now, one of the laws of שביעית
shevi'is is that if you- the stuff that you gathered from the
הפקר or from non-protected and you have in your house and you're
sort of eating off of it during the שמיטה shmita year, you
can only keep it in your house as long as it's available
to animals out in the field. Once there's not any of it
any more available to animals out in the field, you have to
get it out of your house. That's called ביעור. bi'ur. So if
that's a subset... so that's one of the laws of שביעית. shevi'is.
So that law applies- the rest- then you're dealing with something that
all the laws of שביעית shevi'is apply to. ויש שיש לו שביעית,
v'yesh sheyesh lo shevi'is, there's some things that the other laws of
שביעית shevi'is apply to that you have to make הפקר, you can't
do business with and so on, ואין לו ביעור v'ein lo bi'ur
but you don't have to get rid of- out- out of your
house. So what's the case? So let's take a look at the
גמרא. So the case where they both apply is כגון עלי הלוף
שוטה והדנדנה. kegon alei haluf shoteh vehadandana. So the leaves of these
two plants, somebody help me here, what are the two plants? Anybody?
Charlie? It doesn't say. Or לוף. luf. Well, one is mint, but
it doesn't translate לוף. luf. Okay, anyway, the leaves of these two
plants are things which the laws of ביעור bi'ur apply and the-
all the laws of שביעית shevi'is apply. Now, ויש שיש לו שביעית
ואין לו ביעור, v'yesh sheyesh lo shevi'is v'ein lo bi'ur, pretty much
most things are that way. But we're going to do this because
we're contrasting the leaves to the roots. עיקר הלוף שוטה ועיקר הדנדנה.
ikar haluf shoteh v'ikar hadandana. So it is the roots of this
שוטה לוף, shoteh luf, this stupid לוף luf or whatever it's called
anyway, and the- and this הדנדנה. hadandana. Now, why- so although the
leaves it- ביעור bi'ur does apply, the roots it does not apply.
Why does ביעור bi'ur not apply to the roots? Let's take a
look. דכתיב, dichtiv, because here's the law of בי- of ביעור. bi'ur
ולבהמתך ולחיה אשר בארצך תהיה כל תבואתה לאכול. velivhemtcha velachaya asher b'artzecha
tihyeh chol tevu'ata leechol. For the animals and the- and the wild
animals in your land all of- all of the produce shall be-
for eating. כל זמן שחיה אוכלת מן השדה, kol zman shechaya ochelet
min hasadeh, as long as the animals out in the field have
access to these things that they're still growing out in the field,
then אתה מאכיל לבהמתך בבית. ata ma'achil livhemtcha babayit. It's compressing חיה
chaya to בהמה. behema חיה chaya is out in the field, בהמה
is in your house. בהמה are the domesticated. If the חיה chaya
has access to... them in the wild, you can continue to feed
to your animals at home, you can keep them in your house.
כלה לבהמתך שבבית כלה לחיה מן השדה. Kalah livehemtecha shebabayit kalah lachayah
min hasadeh. It's not accessible to the animals out in the wild,
this type of food anymore, כלה לבהמתך שבבית, Kalah livehemtecha shebabayit, you
can no longer have it in your home. והני, V'hanei, and these
things, the roots of these plants, לא כלו להו, lo chalu lehu,
they never get to- they're always available out in the wild at
all times. So basically, it's not a halachic difference, it's just a
circumstantial difference. They basically if שמיטה shmita laws apply, all שמיטה shmita
laws apply, but there's some things that you'll never have to do
ביעור bi'ur on. What are the things you'll never have to do
ביעור bi'ur. on? The things that are always available out in the
field at all times, things that are always growing and are always
accessible, those types of things you'll never have to do ביעור. And
the example was the roots of these two types of plants. Okay,
now we'll take another משנה, this is going to be fun. כל
שיש לו קשקשת יש לו סנפיר, Kol sheyeish lo kaskeset yeish lo
snapir, anything with- right, isn't this- we actually had this in חולין,
Chullin, it's a nice collection of anything with A has B, but
there's things with B without A. Anything that has scales has fins.
ויש שיש לו סנפיר ואין לו קשקשת, Veyeish sheyeish lo snapir ve'ein
lo kaskeset, some things have fins without scales. כל שיש לו קרנים
יש לו טלפיים, Kol sheyeish lo karnayim yeish lo telafayim, most people
don't know this word. If anything has horns, it has split hooves,
so any animal with horn you know it has split hooves, for
kosher reasons. ויש שיש לו טלפיים, Veyeish sheyeish lo telafayim, there are
some animals with split hooves, ואין לו קרנים, ve'ein lo karnayim, doesn't
have horns, a pig. Pig has split hooves, doesn't have horns. Now
we're going to focus just on the first one. Really? Rebbe Aina
says what about the קרנאים, karnayim, it's a one horn, but okay,
but that would be- has two horns. Yeah, it has two horns,
yeah. Or a short one and a long one. Oh right. I
don't think they're the same. They're not the same type of horn.
Type of horn. Yeah, the רש"י Rashi says that, or some other
things as well. Right. Okay. כל שיש לו קשקשת דג טהור, Kol
sheyeish lo kaskeset dag tahor, so now this is going to be
the most generic among- anything that has a scales has fins. Oh,
kosher fish. So ויש לו סנפיר, veyeish lo snapir, it has fins.
ויש שיש לו סנפיר ואין לו קשקשת, Veyeish sheyeish lo snapir ve'ein
lo kaskeset, there's something that have fins that don't have scales. What's
that? דג טמא. Dag tamei. Actually a lot of non-kosher fish don't
have either. It would have been more interesting to tell me a
specific example of a non-kosher fish. I think catfish, right? Catfish has
fins and doesn't have scales. Shark. Shark. Right. Okay. מכדי, Michdi, let's
take a look. אנן אקשקשת סמכינן, Anan akaskeset samchinan, at the end
of the day we rely on scales. סנפיר דכתב רחמנא למה לי,
Snapir dechtav rachmana lamah li, why does the Torah have to tell
me fins? Really it's all determined by scales. אי לא כתב רחמנא
סנפיר, Ei lo chtav rachmana snapir, had it not said fins, הוה
אמינא, havah amina, I would have thought מאי קשקשת דכתיב סנפיר, mai
kaskeset dechtiv snapir, I wouldn't have known what the word קשקשת kaskeset
meant. I would have said maybe that word means fins. So therefore
it says both, ואפילו דג טמא, va'afilu dag tamei, I would have
said- made kosher, non-kosher fish. כתב רחמנא סנפיר ובקשקשת, Ktav rachmana snapir
uv'kaskeset, says both that I have to know well, what are the
two things obviously that it most probably would refer to would be
fins and scales. So by saying both I know that one of
them is fins. So that's a little funny. The גמרא's not so
thrilled with that answer. The גמרא says והשתא דכתב רחמנא סנפיר, v'hashta
dechtav rachmana snapir, that's what the גמרא's going to say, והשתא דכתב
רחמנא סנפיר ובקשקשת, v'hashta dechtav rachmana snapir uv'kaskeset, now the Torah wrote
both and you don't have a way to get out of it.
How do you know מנלן דקשקשת לבושא הוא, manlan dekaskeset levusha hu,
how do you know that קשקשת kaskeset means scales, some type of
clothing? דכתיב, Dechtiv, it says by גלית, Galyat, by Goliath, ושריון קשקשים
הוא לבוש, v'shiryon kaskasim hu lavush, he was wearing armor of scales,
scale armor. Okay, so right, so you see from there we know
that it means scales. Okay, very nice. Now you're admitting that you
know it means scales. So we're back to our first question. Why
did the Torah have to say fins? לכתוב רחמנא קשקשת ולא בעי
סנפיר, Lichtov rachmana kaskeset velo ba'ei snapir, now that you've admitted you
know what scales are, that the word קשקשת kaskeset means scales, why
did the Torah have to say fins? אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi
Abbahu, וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, vechen tana devei Rabbi Yishmael, יגדיל
תורה ויאדיר. yagdil Torah veya'adir. The Torah should be made great and
beautiful. Which I don't get exactly the answer. Maybe the יגדיל תורה
ויאדיר yagdil Torah veya'adir is that you should understand that anything with
scales automatically has fins, but I don't know how you would get
that from the fact that the Torah wrote fins. So I don't
really- I'm open for suggestions about what the answer means. Just as,
you know, it's better to be more loquacious. That's in opposition to
every other assumption of the גמרא, right? So I don't know. Anyway,
one more משנה, not anything convincing. כל הטעון ברכה לאחריו טעון ברכה
לפניו, Kol hata'un berachah l'acharav ta'un berachah l'fanav, anything that you give
a ברכה berachah at the end you have a ברכה berachah at
the beginning. Right, there's no type of event that you do, food
or מצוה mitzvah or anything you do that has a- end ברכה
berachah without a ברכה berachah that precedes it. Sometimes just the whole
thing. I mean you say גומל, Gomel, there's no like- there's no
first ברכה. berachah. Okay. ויש שטעון ברכה לפניו ואין טעון ברכה לאחריו,
Veyeish sheta'un berachah l'fanav ve'ein ta'un berachah l'acharav, some things you have
a ברכה berachah at the outset but you don't have a ברכה
berachah after. So let's take a look at what those things are.
Right. So לאתויי מאי, L'atuyei mai, what is the example here? לאתויי
ירק. L'atuyei yerak. So interestingly, we'll discuss
this more when we do ברכות, Berachot, don't have
to discuss it now. ברכות Berachot is around the corner. There's an
opinion that when you eat vegetables, vegetables are not so sating, not
so significant, you don't make a ברכה אחרונה, bracha achrona, you just
make a ברכה ראשונה, bracha rishona, not a ברכה אחרונה. bracha achrona.
So that would be an example that you have a ברכה bracha
at the beginning and not at the end. ולרבי יצחק דמברך אירק,
Ul'Rabbi Yitzchak d'mivarech a yerak, Rabbi Yitzchak does make a ברכה אחרונה
bracha achrona on vegetables, which obviously is what we do. לאתויי מאי,
l'atuye mai, what would be an example? לאתויי מיא, l'atuye maya, water.
Water as well, it's not really food, it's not really sating, so
therefore it's quenching thirst but it's not sating. You would make a
ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona but not a ברכה אחרונה. bracha achrona. You'd
make a בורא נפשות. Borei Nefashos. Right, you wouldn't according to some
opinions. ורב פפא דמברך אמיא, U'Rav Papa d'mivarech a maya, and according
to Rav Papa, like we do, who says a ברכה אחרונה bracha
achrona on water. לאתויי מאי, l'atuye mai, what would it include? לאתויי
מצוות. l'atuye mitzvos. Okay, ברכת המצוות. birchas hamitzvos. Right, you make a
ברכה bracha at the beginning, you don't make a ברכה bracha at
the end. I would say מצות. matzos. Oh yes, okay, well that's
an example of מצוות. mitzvos. ולבני מערבא דמברכי בתר דשליקי תפילייהו, Ul'vnei
ma'arava d'mivarchi basar d'shiliki tfillaihu, and according to those in the land
of the west, ארץ ישראל, they make a ברכה bracha when they
take off their תפילין, tfillin, the ברכה bracha of לשמור חוקיו, lishmor
chukav, because it says ושמרת את החקה הזאת למועדה מימים ימימה, v'shamarta
es hachuka hazos l'mo'ada m'yamim yamima, which is at the end of
the פרשה parsha of תפילין. tfillin. It might be referring to the
קורבן פסח Korban Pesach but probably is, but according to one דרשה
drasha it's referring to תפילין, tfillin, and that points to the idea
that תפילין, tfillin, it's not just the act of putting on תפילין,
tfillin, תפילין tfillin is about גוף נקי guf naki and keeping your
consciousness, and therefore there's an idea of being שומר תפילין, shomer tfillin,
right, so it's a constant type of a thing. So they seal,
make when they take it off, they make the ברכה bracha לשמור
חוקיו. lishmor chukav. So there they do make a ברכה bracha at
the end of מצוות. mitzvos. Now תוספות points out, this is only
by תפילין tfillin because of the פסוק, because of the idea of
שמירה, shmira, so the גמרא could have said all the other מצוות,
mitzvos, שופר, shofar, ציצית, tzitzis, everything else, סוכה, sukkah, etc., but it
wanted to find maybe an entire category. So yes, it could have
said other מצוות, mitzvos, but the גמרא said ושמרת את החקה הזאת
לשמור חוקיו. v'shamarta es hachuka hazos lishmor chukav. לאתויי מאי, l'atuye mai,
what would be the category of things that you only have a
first ברכה bracha and not an end ברכה? bracha? לאתויי ריחני, l'atuye
reichani, ברכה bracha on smell. A ברכה bracha on smell, there's no
such thing as an end ברכה, bracha, but there is a beginning
ברכה, bracha, and that would be the example of that. And with
this we finish all of this digression of "A" doesn't have "B",
and tomorrow we get back to standard הלכות נידה. Hilchos Niddah.